<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<Chapter>
<Heading>Installation of the Package</Heading> 

Installation of the ANU NQ is done in two steps.

<Section>
<Heading>Configuring for compilation</Heading>
First the configure script is run:
<Listing Type="Installation"> ./configure  </Listing>

If you installed the package in another <Q><F>pkg</F></Q> directory than
the standard <Q><F>pkg</F></Q> directory in your &GAP; 4 installation,
then you have to do two things. Firstly during compilation you have to
use the option <C>--with-gaproot=PATH</C> of the <F>configure</F> script
where <Q>PATH</Q> is a path to the main &GAP; root directory (if not
given the default <Q><F>../..</F></Q> is assumed). That is, run
<Listing Type="Installation"> ./configure --with-gaproot=PATH </Listing>

Secondly you have to specify the path to the directory containing your
<Q><F>pkg</F></Q> directory to &GAP;'s list of directories. This can be
done by starting &GAP; with the <Q><F>-l</F></Q> command line option
followed by the name of the directory and a semicolon. Then your
directory is prepended to the list of directories searched. Otherwise
the package is not found by &GAP;. Of course, you can add this option to
your &GAP; startup script.
<P/>

Another issue that can occur when running <F>configure</F> is that it
may fail to locate the the GNU multiple precision library (GMP
<Cite Key="GNUMP"/>) which ANU NQ requires to work. This library is also
used by &GAP; and hence normally should be available on your system
anyway. But if this is not the case for some reason, it has to be
installed first. A copy of GMP can be obtained from
<URL>http://gmplib.org/</URL>.
<P/>

In order for the <F>configure</F> script to find your copy of GMP, you
may have tell it where to find it via <C>--with-gmp=PATH</C>, where
<Q>PATH</Q> is the path where GMP was installed:

<Listing Type="Installation"> ./configure --with-gmp=PATH </Listing>
Yf necessary, you may combine <C>--with-gmp</C> and
<C>--with-gaproot</C>.

</Section>

<Section>
<Heading>Compiling the nq binary</Heading>

If <F>configure</F> reports no problems, the next step is to start the
compilation:
<Listing Type="Installation"> make </Listing>

<P/> A compiled version of the program named <F>nq</F> is then placed
into the directory <F>bin/&tlt;complicated name&tgt;</F>.  The
&tlt;complicated name&tgt; component encodes the operating system
and the compiler used.  This allows you to compile NQ on several
architectures sharing the same files system.

<P/>
If there are any warnings or even fatal error messages during the
compilation process, please submit a bug report about that
following the instructions in Section <Ref Sect="feedback" Style="Number"/>

</Section>

<Section>
<Heading>Testing</Heading>

After the compilation is finished you can check if the ANU NQ
is running properly on your system.  Simply type

<Listing Type="Installation"> make test </Listing>

This runs some computations and compares their output with the output
files in the directory <F>examples</F>. If any errors are reported, please
follow the instructions below.

</Section>

<Section Label="feedback">
<Heading>Feedback</Heading>

If you encounter problems with any of the above steps, please do not
hesitate to contact us about this.  You can either use the
<URL Text="nq issue tracker">https://github.com/gap-system/nq/issues</URL>
or contact the GAP support group via <Email>support@gap-system.org</Email>.
Please make sure to include information about the specific issue
you encountered (e.g. steps to reproduce it, the specific error message),
your operating system, the compiler you used
and also the versions of &GAP; and this package that were involved.

</Section>

</Chapter>
